[Music]
[Applause]
should the gluteus maximus be trained at
long muscle length or short muscle
length for maximum results in this video
I'm going to roll through the four
existing studies pertaining to glus Max
Muscle length uh I'm going to discuss
the available evidence and then talk
about physiological concerns that we
still need to figure out I'm going to
list off the 10 longitudinal studies
that need to be conducted for us to
really have a good picture to allow us
to answer the question and I'm going to
finish off with nine important
considerations so I hope you're prepared
to kind of put on your nerdy
biomechanics hat for a while because
this is going to be a little bit
scientific it's not going to be as sexy
of a topic as some of my other videos
but it's not just very important it's
vital for the future direction of glute
training at the very least I'm very
excited about this topic and I hope that
shows through so right now there are
four studies one by Kubo one by casano
one by Plotkin and one by Mau but there
are 25 total studies on this muscle
length debate pertaining to all the
muscle groups okay so four of the 25
pertain to the gluteus maximus but 21
belong to other muscle now in general
the evidence shows that training muscles
at longer muscle lengths is more
effective than training them at Short
muscle Lanes now the problem is almost
all of these studies are on beginners
and here's what's hilarious kind of a
recent topic there are already seven
review papers on the topic and this
topic is gaining momentum if you're in
the strength training and sports science
Realms then you hear about this topic
all the time and right now the pendulum
has swung towards longer Lanes but is
there a role for shorter length training
especially for the gluteus maximus and
how can we get to the bottom of this
debate so the the Kubo study showed that
deeper squats were more effective at
building the gluteus maximus than
shallower squats now I'm skeptical of
these results and the reason why is
because they only mention knee angle
they didn't mention hip angle okay so
you can squat very upright and just move
your knees forward and achieve a certain
knee angle and barely work your glutes
conversely if you get a wide stance take
a low bar position and sit way back and
spread the knees you're going to feel
your glutes a lot so you can achieve the
same knee angle in two different
scenarios but one of them has you
feeling all quads one has you filling
all glutes they did not show pictures in
this study and I emailed the authors and
never heard back so skeptical of Kubo
the next paper is by ciano and this
study showed that if you do leg press
and stiff leg deadlifts and then you add
hip thrust to it you see better results
so basically one group did leg press and
stiff leg deadlift the other group did
leg press stiff leg deadlift and hip
Thro thrust and the group that did hip
thrust saw better results the problem
with this study is was it due to just
more volume in general or was it
something special about hip thrust the
study wasn't designed to answer that
question but it did show that hip
thrusts do work they do build glute
muscle the third paper is by plin now I
was involved in this study my buddy meno
henselman and I funded it and it looked
at squats versus hip thrust and it found
that squats and hip thrust built the
glutes fairly equally as well so this
showed pretty much a one toone
relationship between squats and hip dust
for building glutes now squats were more
effective at building the quads and the
adductors and neither exercise built the
hamstrings or glute medius to much
degree and finally we have the recent ma
abstract and it basically looked at
straight leg hip extensions off the
multi-hit machine it looked at two
ranges of motion basically a full range
of motion versus a partial range of
motion but the full range of motion
wasn't really full and the partial range
of motion didn't stretch the glutes that
well because it's straight-legged so if
you really wanted to look at the effects
of muscle length you should have taken
the glutes into a deeper stretch by
performing bent leg uh hip extensions
and then finally you should have went
all the way back into full hip extension
full hip hyper extension they went to
neutral they went to zero degrees they
should have went into full hip
hyperextension which is like you know
textbooks and like studies will show
about 15 to 20° but in real life when
you train people they move that leg back
pretty far so my guess is that this was
I mean to me this was just comparing
like you know partial to partial but
they didn't maximize muscle length or
muscle shortness so this study didn't
look at a big glute stretch or a big
glute squeeze so in my opinion it was
designed more to pertain to sprinting
because they wanted to look at the
effects on sprinting so as of July 30th
the time I'm filming this video there
are only four relevant papers to the
gluteus maximus so before I get started
into the studies that need to take place
to answer this question I want to
discuss some physiological concerns that
we need to figure out and there are
basically four of them that we really
need to answer to allow us to make
predictions to form theories ideally the
theories would match experiments you
know it's nice when you really
understand the mechanisms responsible
for the hypertrophy but right now we
don't know enough yet so one really
important physiological mechanism that
we need to look at is when you get down
into the bottom of a squat the glute Max
is not activated highly now people say
oh EMG this EMG that but if a muscle is
not activated highly then how would it
grow maximally because if if it just
about stretching a muscle then people
did yoga would be jacked and all you do
is sit there and stretch now there are
studies showing stretch does build
muscle but it's very inefficient you
know you can stretch a muscle like 3
hours a week and get the same muscle
growth that takes you you know 20
minutes in the gym so I have not
published this yet but I have had 12
subjects get into the bottom of a squat
and I load the bar up with too much
weight they can't actually squat the
weight up but they get under the bar
they get in their squat position and
they push up as hard as they can for 5
seconds okay then without moving they
push out against their their knees are
blocked they're in the same exact
position there's a bench on the left and
right side of their knees and they push
out as hard as they can so basically
you're in deep flexion and you're
performing hip extension then hip
abduction basically on average you're
firing the glutes two to three times
harder when you push out in deep hip
flexion compared to pushing up so in
deep hip flexion the glutes appear to be
more abductors than extensors so I would
love for this to be duplicated I I wish
a few different Labs showed this you
know I can Envision the title of the
paper being in deep hip flexion the
primary role of the gluteus maximus is
abduction not extension that would
really blow people's minds because we
think when you're in a deep stretch the
glutes are in a good position to push
upwards and get you out of the hole but
they're not firing as hard as they could
be so hopefully this gets published and
a bunch of other labs confirm it so if
you're a master student or a PhD student
you're looking for a study to perform
please carry this out on your own we
could talk about surfice EMG and muscle
length but keep in mind you're in the
same exact position muscle length
doesn't change so surface EMG is fine
here but we could also use other tools
to measure motor unit recruitment there
as well the second physiological
mechanism which might help explain the
first is this neuromechanical matching
Theory basically the theory states that
as a muscle gains leverage or as a
muscle improves its moment arm which is
a term for leverage then basically the
nervous system recruits that muscle to a
greater degree and that makes sense
basically if the brain and the central
nervous system was trying to be
efficient it would know this muscle has
good leverage it's effective in this
position so I'm going to activate it to
a higher degree now we do have a bunch
of moment arm studies I think last time
I counted there were like eight um the
first being nemith which I've referenced
a lot over the years and we do know that
as the glutitis Maximus progresses from
Deep hip flexion a deep stretch to full
hip extension its leverage does improve
maximum Leverage is it you know around
neutral um and it's like probably 2 and
a half times greater at around neutral
than it is in deep hip flexion so we do
have EMG studies but most of it's using
surface EMG ideally we'd have more
sophisticated technology to ascertain
whether the gluteus maximus does in fact
ramp up its neural drive from flexion to
extension moving on there are no studies
published on the length tension
relationship of the glutitis Maximus now
I'm talking about the active passive and
total Force angle curves meaning how
much force does the the glutitis Maximus
produce in deep hip flexion all the way
to full hip extension now bear in mind
that there's active force and passive
Force active force is produced when a
muscle is activated it's more of the
sarir Contracting right passive force is
elastic it's nonactivated it's
independent of activation it's just via
stretch now when a muscle is activated
and stretched it does produce greater
force but we really need to look at
bodybuilders we need to look at
hypertrophied glutes and really look at
the Active passive and total Force angle
curves because bodybuilders have big
muscular glutes where is maximum active
Force production is it towards neutral
is it in a stretch is it at 15° 30° of
hip flection and how much passive Force
do you get now here's the deal
biomechanists like me like to use open
SIM it's a free software that lets you
plot all these different curves you can
look at the active and passive and total
Force angle curve curs of the gluteus
maximus but you get totally different
results depending on the model you use
so I use this Raja goal model from 2015
and if you use that model you get one
plot and there's another catalini I
think 2017 model and if you use that
model it gives you a totally different
plot and if you really delve into the
software you look at what changed the
authors Chang like the tendon slack and
that produces a totally different curve
now how do you even estimate tendon
slack for the glutitis Maximus are the
modelers just plugging in data trying to
make it fit are they basing this off
relevant physiological data and with the
gluteus maximus you've got a lot of
fascia 70 to 85% of the glus Maximus
attaches to fascia not bone so it's an
interesting challenging muscle to model
and the fourth physiological mechanism
to investigate would be corticospinal
excitability in different joint angle
configurations so there's one study
published on the arm like you know the
arm muscle Muses and it it basically
looked at the you know nervous systems
excitability like its preparedness to
activate in different arm positions you
know the biceps and triceps were it was
I can't remember the paper that was it's
been a while but there were different
POS there were unique positions that
maximize neural drive to the muscles and
that might influence hypertrophy we may
find over time that we should be putting
the muscles in that position but it
would be nice to look at that for the
glutitis Maximus particularly in deep
stretched positions you know versus
shortened positions so now I've
discussed some physiological mechanisms
that need to be ascertained to really
help us form theories theories without
experiments are just hypothetical you
need experiments to match theories and
experiments are the most important thing
experiments tell you what does happen
not what should happen so here are the
longitudinal training studies
longitudinal means a training study
meaning you do some pre-testing you
carry car out an intervention lasting
say you know 6 to 12 weeks usually and
then you do Post testing and you see
what actually happen when you put these
people through a resistance training
program now there are four studies
looking at isometrics and the effect of
isometrics at different muscle lengths
on muscle hypertrophy I have four new
ideas just for the gluteus maximus now
these 10 studies are going to progress
from kind of more proof of principle to
more ecologically valid meaning to prove
a principle you'll have to keep things
very isolated and very simple but it
usually doesn't match what we do in the
real world but a lot of times what we do
in the real world it doesn't really
answer the question well I'll explain
this more later the first is to perform
electric muscle stimulation at long
versus short muscle length so I don't
think this would convince everyone it
would just be an easy study to do have
people hook up Ems now EMS grows muscle
too I didn't think it did but there's a
ton of evidence in support of EMS in
fact I bought an electric muscle
stimulator and I use it on my clients
all the time um when they're visiting
but yeah I basically um I thought it
would be fun you can watch TV and grow
muscle but it's actually kind of
stressful it hurts you have in order for
it to be effective you have to crank up
the intensity it's not fun but you could
have EMS done at Short muscle lengths
and at long muscle LS and see which led
to Greater growth that's an easy one now
the second idea that I have is is my
favorite my favorite of all 10 studies
seated glute squeeze versus standing
glute squeeze so these are isometrics
it'd be very a very easy training
program because you could have people do
it a lot you could probably tell people
you know do it for 20 minutes a day try
to basically you know be leaning forward
and squeeze your glutes you know flex
your glutes as hard as you can off and
on for 20 minutes every day for like you
know two months or something like that
and then also have people standing
squeezing their glutes as hard as they
can see if there are any differences
that would be a very effective study now
the third and fourth isometric ideas I
don't like quite as much but you could
do a multi- hiip machine or an
isokinetic dynamometer the multi- hiip
is done standing the dynamometer is some
of them are standing but a lot of them
are Supine and you could basically have
people do isometric you know hip
extension in a long muscle length versus
a short muscle length like deep stretch
versus full hip extension I don't like
these because if you've used these it's
kind of it doesn't feel as natural
single legegg stuff doesn't feel quite
as natural and like when you're standing
you know doing isometrics you can you
you know this the stretch feels better
with the multi- hiip but at end range
you kind of you almost need to stabilize
yourself because gravity is not
stabilizing you it's that front hip
flexor stabilizing you so I don't like
these that idea as much and then also
you could do hip thrust isometric you
could do this double leg in which case
basically have people do isometrics in
the bottom of a hip thrust they push up
as hard as they can and then they do the
hip thrust lock out push up as hard as
they can which group sees better results
the group that does long length
isometrics or the glute that does short
length isometrics now you could also do
a single leg study um and you could do
single leg hip thrust basically single
hip thrust in the bottom single hip
thrust in the top and when you use this
study design It's very effective because
you could have each subject serve as
their own control meaning every subject
like one leg does like a single leg hip
thrust in the bottom position and the
other leg does it at the top position so
each participant serves as their own
control it increases statistical power
which glute grew more the one that did
in the stretch position or the squeezed
position now the fifth idea has to do
with full range versus partials now
there are 11 existing studies looking at
full range versus partials and there are
three studies this is a more recent
field of of interest looking at partials
in the stretch versus partials in the
shorten position so 14 total studies
looking at basically full range versus
partials or partials in the stretch
versus partials in the squeeze now I
have one main idea for the glutitis
Maximus and that's to perform thrusts or
squats or both I think it would be
awesome to do both squats and hip thrust
so basically you could have three groups
with the Plotkin study that meno and I
funded we each spent 40 G so it's
$80,000 because you want to use MRI so
to have three groups would be 120 Grand
so these don't get carried out very
often but it would be cool to have three
groups one group that does full range
squats and hip thrust the next group
does bottom partials for squats and hip
thrust and then the third group does top
partials for squats and hip thrust and
what what I like about doing squats and
hip thrust you know the Deep squat feels
a little natural for the glutes than the
top squat but the top of the hipos feels
more natural for glutes than the bottom
of the hip disk so it's balanced in in
my opinion now there are seven existing
studies right now looking at differing
torque angle curves um basically the
effect of the strength curve on muscle
growth now you can have an exercise that
works you hard in the stretch but it's
easy at the lock out or you could have a
muscle that's easy in the stretch and
hard at the lock out one example of that
is the Plotkin paper squats are harder
for the glutes in the stretch position
whereas hip thrusts are harder for the
glutes in the squeeze position so
there's seven existing papers on this
and I have five different ideas on this
topic for the gluteus maximus now the
Plotkin paper already looked at hip
thrust versus squats but a lot of the
Skeptics said well why they choose
squats why didn't they choose rdl's why
didn't they choose lunges why didn't
they choose single leg leg presses so
it'd be nice to have a study like the
Plotkin study but looking at hip thrust
versus rdls or lunges or single leg leg
press now the second idea would be the
same single leg design I already
mentioned where each subject served as
their own control but it would require
really strong subjects very Advanced
subjects because you'd want to use a
Smith machine here so that each exercise
was very stable but you'd have basically
each subject on one leg they would do
Smith machine single leg squats and I
don't think it should be a ler split
squat cuz you're really that's not
everything on one leg because the other
leg is going to do single leg hip thrust
and you want it the other leg in the air
you could do B stance but if you do B
stance you're going to use that glute a
little bit so one group one leg
basically does the squatting motion
where it's hardest at the bottom and the
other leg is going to do the single leg
hip thrusting motion which is hardest at
the top and you see which glute GLW
better so again you can have if you have
20 subjects you'd have huge cical power
and you'd only need one MRI cuz you
could look at each glue independently
now the next idea is my second favorite
idea next to the isometric CED standing
glute squeeze idea that I had and this
is to use band or chains or both
basically you're going to use bands and
chains with squats or hip thrust or both
I think it should be both of them so one
group does basically squats and hip
thrust using accommodating resistance
meaning at the bottom you know it's say
I I did chain squats the other day at
the bottom I had 225 but I had 130 lbs
of chain so at the top it was 225 plus
13 30 so is that 355 I did a set of 10
and my glutes were screaming I felt my
glutes more during chain squats than I
do during regular squats and the last
couple reps kind of felt like a hip
thrust because it's way harder at the
top so there currently aren't many
studies looking at hypertrophy with
bands and chains there's tons of studies
looking at strength but I'm not sure if
there's a single study looking at uh
band like barbell plus band resistance
on muscle growth so this would be pretty
cool and then the other group would just
do regular free weight um you know Barb
squats and hip thrust so you'd have to
kind of try to um equate load somehow
but basically one group would just
perform straight weight and the other
group would do a comod this where it's
easier at the bottom harder at the top
so that's a study I would really like to
carry out the next example would be
awesome but these don't quite exist yet
for the glute Drive have you guys ever
used the Hammer Strength they call it
the squat lunge machine but everyone
does deadlifts off of it if you look at
the top loading pin it starts out
further away from the fulcrum and as you
rise up it moves closer so basically the
resistance arm starts out longer and
ends shorter meaning it gets easier
throughout the range of motion meaning
it's harder in the stretch now the
Rogers pendulum squat allows for the
same exact thing with the squat so you
can choose a loading placement where
it's harder at the bottom easier at the
top and then both machines also have a
different loading mechanism that makes
it more consistent throughout the range
of motion so you could design machines
that had
like think of in the case of a a hip
thrust or the squat of the deadlift
basically where when you're at the very
bottom it's straight out and then as you
rise up it moves closer to the fulcrum
meaning it gets easier and then you
could have another loading placement
that's down like this where it's closer
to the fulcrum and then as you move
through the range of motion it gets
harder it comes out further it swings up
and you could make them complete
opposites one of one another so that
they have opposite strength curves and
you could have one group do say squats
and hip thrusts you could add in
deadlifts it could be just squats just
hip thrust um just deadlist or all three
or two of them say squats and hip thrust
similar to bands and chains but
basically one group does it where all
the loading is in the bottom and it gets
really easy as you come up versus the
group that does all the loading at the
top and it's easier at the bottom that
would be a really cool study but this
doesn't exist yet for the glute Drive
machines but I am working on that right
now and then the 10th idea for a
training study which would probably be
the most ecologically valid would just
to be a vertical hip extension training
program versus horizontal okay so
basically and this was funny when Mike
Roberts and Daniel Plotkin came to me
this is what they wanted to do I've
talked about this idea for I think like
12 years now uh I remember blogging
about years ago that this needs to be
done vertical versus horizontal hip
extension exercises so basically one
group would do say pick three of these
squats rdl's lunges step up split squats
you then pick three of these basically
hip thrust glute Bridges back extensions
cable Kickbacks so basically say on
Monday the vertical group does squats
Wednesday they do rdl's Friday they do
lunges and the horizontal group Monday
they do hip thrusts you know Wednesday
they do Kickbacks and Friday they do
back extensions which group grows their
glutes better and that would be very
ecologically valid because this is what
people are doing in real life so each of
those 10 training studies and the four
physiological experiments that I mention
those will be 14 puzzle pieces that
would really help us form a big picture
of what's more effective training at
long versus short Glu muscle Lanes
however I do want to mention nine
considerations here that you really need
to think about and the first one is
Advanced subjects there are no studies
on the glutes using Advanced subjects
and very few in General using Advanced
subjects on out of all the 25 currently
published papers only a couple of them
use Advanced subjects so we need more
studies looking at Advanced lifters the
second consideration is combined groups
now as I mentioned MRIs are very
expensive so in the Plotkin paper we
wanted a combined group but it would
have been 40 Grand more also in general
research is carried out by students for
example Daniel Plotkin is Mike Roberts
PhD student right now he oversaw the
squat vers hip thrust paper you got to
do it in one semester and you're limited
in Manpower you know you can have your
fellow students and colleagues help you
but having like 60 subjects would be a
nightmare that's why you don't see a lot
of these in sports science but it it
would be cool to see a combined group
because because in the real world we
don't have to choose between long or
short muscle length we can do them both
and that's what all bodybuilders
currently do you know if they're
training biceps they might do an incline
curl you know basically leaning leaning
back on an incline to stretch the muscle
they might do a preacher curl to really
load up the stretch they might do a
concentration curl to load up the
squeeze position they might do a hammer
curl you know to work The Brak yice more
but basically most bodybuilders do a
combination of long length stretch
movements short length squeeze movements
so if the combined group saw better
results than the stretch or the squeeze
group than the long or short group then
that kind of validates what bodybuilders
do and it'll also paint to multiple
mechanisms of hypertrophy right now we
don't know what grows muscle what are
the signals and sensors we think Titan
is important Titan would be important
with an activated stretch but what about
nuclear flattening you know the nucleus
flattening out what about the sarir
squeezing together are there anything in
those Z discs like you know filament 3
bag C or whatever bag 3 filament C that
senses that and responds to activation
what structures of the cell are sensing
you know the forces and then converting
those you know through mechano
transduction into chemical signals is it
the Titan filament is it you know the
nucleus is it the primary cyia of
satellite cells is it the extracellular
Matrix is it the integrin is every
structure involved or is it just limited
to like you know one or two or three
things we don't really know but that
would be a cool proof of principle paper
for multiple mechanisms of hypertrophy
the third consideration is a lateral
group you know we're mentioning long
versus short muscle LS but it's all hip
extension what about abduction it'd be
cool to look at abduction because
abduction grows the glutitis medius the
best in our Plotkin paper squats and
hypos did not grow the glute medius
substantially well the glut medius and
Minimus are part of the glutes but no
one talks about lateral movement the
fourth consideration is using different
volumes and frequency in the Plotkin
paper we did twice a week you know
between three and six sets per session
but but you know hip thrusts don't beat
you up as much as squats well it might
be that long length is more efficient
but short length you can do more volume
with so maybe short length with you
really load up the volume maybe short
length is more effective than long
length at really high volumes and
frequencies so for example what if you
hip thrusted 5 days a week would you see
better
glutithione you know the groups were
told you can train as soon as you feel
recovered so maybe the squat group ends
up squatting you know twice a week maybe
three times a week when they feel
recovered but maybe the hip thrust group
ends up training 5 days a week because
they don't feel so beat up you go by
perceived recovery so it's like an auto
regulated plan based on how you feel in
that case would shorter lengths see
better results than longer lengths who
knows the sixth consideration is looking
at injury and soreness data would the
long length group experience more
dropouts would they experience more
soreness would they more be more
fatigued and beat up by the end of the
study because that influences long-term
results you know cool maybe hammering
squats and deadlifts and lunges is
awesome for your glutes but if you do
too much volume you're going to get
anterior hip pain and femoral acid TBL
impingement syndrome you're going to get
low back pain or like you know injuries
to the discs and ligaments maybe you're
going to have knee pain maybe your quad
or patellar tendons start acting up so
which are safe for longer shorter muscle
lengths does it matter according to the
repeated bat effect we adapt to long
length training in Ecentric but how well
can you adapt and do long length stress
other structures other than the muscle
and does that impact recovery and
overall results the seventh idea was
inspired by my booty by Brett program
and my rule of thirds so I've made a
whole video on the rule of thirds check
it out if you haven't watched it yet but
basically I talk about how in booty
vibret we do 36 sets a week okay in
general like in general okay in general
around a third of those so 12 sets would
be vertical hip extension exercises
another third would be horizontal hip
extension exas and then another third
would be lateral so how cool it be to
have four groups this will never be
conducted this will never be carried out
because it would require four groups
you'd need like at least 15 ideally 20
subjects in each group because you'd
probably have some Dropout so you need
like 80 subjects and you'd need
basically this would cost like you know
sever hundred grand to carry it out it
will never get done but how cool would
this be one group just does the 12 sets
of vertical per week one group just does
the 12 sets of horizontal one group does
the 12 sets of lateral per week and then
one group does all three of them
combined so what this would allow us is
basically we'd say here's an optimal
program you know the optimal program had
you doing a combination of vertical
horizontal and lateral but the vertical
led to this much growth the horizontal
led to this much growth and the lateral
led to this much growth and basically
the lateral built the upper glutes you
know the glute medius and Minimus more
um does lateral contribute to glute
Maximus growth how much you know does
vertical build the lower glutes a little
bit more and horizontal builds the upper
glutes a little bit more that's what I
always thought based on EMG but the
Plotkin study did not show that so this
would be a really really telling study
but it'll probably never occur two more
considerations we need a cheaper way to
carry out these studies unless expensive
way so MRIs are very expensive can you
use ultrasound to look at muscle growth
I've used ultrasound I didn't trust
myself it was hard it was really hard on
certain subjects I did a a twin
experiment I could see the fasal Border
underneath for the twins but I I looked
at a few other subjects like my
girlfriend at the time I kept adjusting
the gain the depth and I could not see
the fascial border and I just didn't
trust it so to use ultrasound you got to
have an experienced technician but is it
other muscles are a lot easier to look
out using ultrasound because like with
the biceps you see the bone you don't
see a bone with the glutitis Maximus so
how does ultrasound using a good skilled
technician stack up against MRI and are
there any other methods using other
technologies that would be more cost
effective CU if so we could crank out a
lot more research and the last the ninth
consideration I want to leave you with
is which ranges of motion should we use
for these studies which exercises what
limb number should we do unilateral or B
lateral you know when you do single leg
hip thrust you don't get as high of
glute activity as when you do double EG
hip thrust should we be using lunges if
so how do we maximize stability should
we use a Smith machine and how deep
should we go what range of motion so if
you're doing lunges should you do
walking lunges or just reverse lunges or
you should you do deficit reverse lunges
in my experience when I do walking
lunges my glutes get more sore than when
I do deficit reverse lunges because when
you do deficit the knee moves forward
you have a forward Shin angle when you
do walking lunges with a long stride or
just reverse lunges you can have a
vertical Shin angle and when the thigh
is roughly parallel you maximize torque
at that bottom position so torque on the
glute is maximized kind of at parallel
depth with squats and lunges and things
like that and if you go deeper the
deeper you go torque starts diminishing
so at long muscle length should we be
aiming to achieve maximum stretch or
maximum torque and in the stretch
position you know should we be trying to
to abduct it all or should we be trying
to externally rotate it all you know I
think the Plotkin paper showed that you
can grow the glutes in beginners Well
from either squats or hip thrust
indicating that muscle length might not
be as important as we thought so does
that mean that if you're doing deadlifts
you could do conventional for greater
stretch or Sumo which theoretically
would be be better for Activation with
the abduction external rotation but
there's only one study looking that with
esam didn't show that but hopefully you
get the point is conventional better
than Sumo is narrow stance with a deeper
stretch more effective than wide stance
these are all things that need to be
figured out over time and these nine
considerations are important with the 14
experiments that I mentioned
nevertheless think of all of this as a
puzzle and you've got all these puzzle
pieces right now we only have a few
puzzle pieces we've got four existing
studies all on beginners we don't have a
grasp of the physiology yet we don't
have nearly enough training studies but
but as we learn more as we gain more
puzzle pieces the big picture becomes
clear and I talked mostly about glutes
but this pertains to all the muscles
right now we should always be striving
for improvements I hear people say oh
everything we learned about strength
training we knew 100 years ago nothing
is new we're always learning new things
and we should always be striving to
maximize our understanding pushing the
envelope for Bing for better training
programs and better understanding of the
mechanisms cuz that allows us to design
better programs okay that's a wrap I
hope you enjoy the video thank you for
watching please hit like if you enjoy
the video please make sure you're
subscribe to my channel and definitely
leave me a comment and let me know what
you think thanks for
watching